SAM MARKHAM SOFTWARE ENGINEER

- sam.e.markham@gmail.com
- https://dev.to/sharkham
- **(**778) 387-0734
- ♦ Vancouver, BC
- in markhamsam
- Sharkham

Technologies

CSS

Git

 HTML

InDesign

JavaScript

Photoshop

Postgres

Rails

React

Redux

Regex (Ruby, JS)

Ruby

SQL

Publications & Conferences

Featured fiction reader, UBC Graduate Conference in Children's Literature (2012 & 2016)

Featured fiction reader, Read Out Loud, Sunshine Coast Pride's queer literary salon (2015)

Interview with Kendare Blake, author of the award-winning Anna Dressed in Blood, published in Nineteen Questions magazine (2014)

Research paper, "Bill C-389: What is the media really saying about transgender rights?" published in Sojourners: Undergraduate Journal of Sociology (2011/2012) Full stack software engineer with experience in Ruby and Javascript, including Rails and React frameworks. My previous adventures include a decade of solving problems through writing, editing, critique and collaboration across many fields, from fiction and a published sociology paper to graphic novels and press releases. My blend of skills in collaboration, communication, analysis and creativity supplement my hard skills in coding. I enjoy putting my mind to a blank page and crafting something tangible and useful.

Education

Flatiron School June 2019 to May 2020 Full Stack Software Engineering, Ruby on Rails and JavaScript program

University of British Columbia BFA Creative Writing & Sociology 2015 Sept. 2009 to May 2015

Projects

Novel Tracker

Apr. 2020 to Present

Github FrontEnd | Github BackEnd | Demo Video | Deployed Demo

An app for writers to keep track of their writing progress in a yearly novel writing contest (Created for Codex Writers' Group, an online community of active speculative fiction writers)

- Developed a Rails API backend with endpoints for users, novels, badges, and badge types
- Backed the API with a Postgres database to facilitate smooth deployment to Heroku
- · Implemented user interface using React and Redux with reactstrap for styling
- Implemented forgot/reset password functionality to prepare for live use
- Deployed backend server to Heroku and frontend to Netlify

PokéTeam Builder

Feb. 2020 to Feb. 2020

Dec. 2019 to Dec. 2019

Github | Demo Video

A tactile way for Pokémon fans to quickly visualize the official heights of their favourite Pokémon

- Scraped PokéApi to populate Rails backend with information on over 300 Pokémon
- Implemented simple user interface using JavaScript click events to allow users to drag images around
- · Styled frontend using Bootstrap to enhance user experience

Collab Writing App

Github | Demo Video

A content management system for writers to keep track of group novel projects

- Utilized OAuth to allow users to sign up with Google
- Implemented has_many_through relationships in Rails to allow users to be collaborators on many novels, and also to allow novels to each have many collaborators
- Used a role-based authorization system and helper methods to whitelist actions to specific user roles

Recent Employment

Harbour Publishing | Douglas & McIntyre Madeira Park, BC | Vancouver, BC Book Publicist Sept. 2014 to Dec. 2017, Mar. 2019 to Mar. 2020

- Utilized writing skills creating and editing a wide variety of marketing materials for 30+ books as lead publicist, including writing and designing press releases, event releases and posters
- Honed coordination and problem-solving skills by designing, setting up, and when necessary, troubleshooting author tours for over 20 authors across Canada and the US
- Gained extensive experience working remotely after relocation to Vancouver in Fall 2015

Freelance

Developmental Editor

2008 to Present

 Employed critique skills and ability to work to deadlines giving professional constructive critique and detailing both grammatical and content edits on written works, including the works of 5+ professionally published authors

Vancouver Symphony Orchestra

Lotteries Assistant

Vancouver, BC Sept. 2013 to Dec. 2013

Managed a large pool of volunteers and processed lottery tickets using the Tessitura database management system